Burning fat in order to lose weight is
probably something all of us have
thought about or at least will think
about at some point in our lives. And
there seems to be endless debates on how
to do it with the best workouts, diets,
[music] and even fat burning zones. So,
what really is the best way to burn fat?
Well, I'm going to say something that
might sound a little bold, and that is
physiologically there is only one way to
burn fat, [music] and this has to do
with the body's energy systems and how
the body metabolizes your
macronutrients, which are proteins,
carbs, and fats. So, today we'll talk
about the only pathway that can
metabolize fat and how this can
influence the type of exercises you
choose to most effectively burn fat.
We'll of course review some of the
different types of fat and how this
influences health and weight loss. And
at the end, we'll give some sample
exercise protocols. We're going to get
into some oily details in this one. So,
let's jump into this anatomical and
physiological awesomeness.
So, let's quickly review some key facts
about fat because not all fat is the
same. Plus, this will definitely help us
to understand the mechanisms involved in
losing fat. Most of what we deal with in
adults is white atapost tissue or white
fat. So, if I use fat or atapost tissue
interchangeably, just know that I'm
talking about the same thing. But here's
an example of this on the cadaavver. And
yes, it is more yellow on this
cadaavver. You can thank the inbalming
process for that because in it would be
more of a white to light yellow color.
This white fat stores energy, provides
padding and insulation, and can build up
under the skin or around the organs,
which means we can also subdivide fat by
its location. Subcutaneous fat sits just
under the skin, but on top of the
muscles, and so it's what hides those
abs and other muscles if it gets thick
enough, because subcutaneous fat can be
millime thick, like on this leg, or
[music]
many centimeters or inches thick, like
on this abdominal dissection. Then
there's visceral fat deeper inside
wrapping around organs like the heart,
liver, and intestines. And this can also
vary in thickness. On this body, you can
see it is thinner and what would be
considered at more of a healthy level.
But on this body, you can see much more
visceral fat and what would be
considered an unhealthy amount. And the
reason I say healthy versus unhealthy
amount is because visceral fat is often
referred to as the more dangerous fat
because excess amounts are more strongly
linked to health issues like type 2
diabetes, heart disease, and high blood
pressure. And studies also show it can
ramp up inflammation and even mess with
insulin sensitivity. And we'll kind of
talk about whether or not you can target
the loss of visceral fat versus
subcutaneous fat a little bit later on.
But there's also brown atapost tissue or
brown fat which is more common in babies
and it gets its color from being packed
with specialized mitochondria and blood
vessels. And unlike white fat, brown fat
burns calories to actually generate
heat. Now adults do have some brown fat,
mostly around the neck and upper back.
And studies suggest cold exposure might
boost it or activate those special
mitochondria which we cover in a lot
more detail in our cold plunge video if
you want to watch that afterwards. But
now we want to understand how atapost
tissue behaves with weight gain and
weight loss. Like what actually happens
when the tissue gets thicker when we
gain weight and what happens when it
gets thinner when we lose weight. Well,
atapose tissue is actually classified as
a connective tissue made up of fat cells
and a loose network of collagen fibers
dispersed between those fat cells. Now
the scientific term for fat cell is
ataposite. So again, if I say fat cell,
atapostite, or atapose cell throughout
the rest of the video, we're talking
about the same thing. But these cells
are like little storage units packed
with triglycerides. And a triglyceride
is a molecule of glycerol bonded to
three fatty acids. And if you were to
gain weight in the form of fat, these
cells would literally fill up with more
triglycerides, which will cause the
cells to get bigger. And as the cells
continue to get bigger, this will cause
the overall fatty tissue to get thicker.
But let's say instead you were to lose
weight from losing fat. And this often
happens from calorie restriction,
exercise, or a combination of the two.
In those situations, signals would be
sent to the fat cells causing the cells
to perform lipolysis. Lipo refers to fat
and lis refers to breakdown. So in this
case, the triglycerides will be broken
down and the fatty acids will be
released from the fat cells. And outside
the fat cells, there are also tiny blood
vessels called capillaries that will
take up the fatty acids. And once in the
blood, that means the fatty acids could
be transported to almost any cells
throughout the body that might need the
fatty acids for energy. And that could
be the quad muscle that you were
repetitively contracting during an
exercise session. And if overall the fat
cells release more fatty acids than they
store, they will shrink. And as the
cells continue to shrink, this will
cause the tissue to get thinner and will
make it easier for you to see those
rippling muscles underneath. But let's
come back to the part where we pulled
the fatty acids out of the fat cells and
into the bloodstream. Remember I said
once in the blood, the fatty acids could
go to almost any cell to supply those
cells with energy. And this includes
muscle cells, which are also often
referred to as muscle fibers. However, I
also said that there is only one way to
burn those fatty acids. And this is
where we get into the three energy
systems of the human body. And with all
this talk about burning fat and the
different energy systems, some of you
might be interested in tracking your
calories in a very cool way. And that's
where the sponsor of today's video comes
in, Calai. Calai is an incredible app
that makes calorie tracking a breeze.
It's as easy as taking a picture. All
you do is snap a picture of your meal
and Cali will analyze the meal by
calculating your calories and macros for
you. Now, one of the things that turned
me off from other calorie trackers is
all the typing and searching that I was
having to do just to find the right
food. But with Cali, you don't have to
do any typing or searching, just
seamless tracking. And from my
experience, it's very accurate. But I
always do make sure to check the
ingredients after the scan to ensure the
AI caught everything from the picture.
And for those of you that want 100%
accuracy, they also have a great barcode
scanner and food database that you can
use to double check. So if you're
interested in dialing in your nutrition
with less hassle, download the app in
the App Store, Google Play Store, or
simply click the link in the description
and use my promo code IOHA for a 3-day
free trial. Thanks to Cali for
supporting the channel. And now let's
get back to the energy systems and
burning fat. Going over these energy
systems is going to help us understand
why there's only one way to burn fat, at
least metabolically. And this will also
help us to choose exercises that could
be more efficient at burning fat. Your
body has three main energy systems to
produce the energy currency of our cells
called adenosine triphosphate or ATP.
And we produce the ATP from the energy
primarily found in carbohydrates and
fats. But we can also use proteins to
produce ATP if needed and also creatine
gets involved. But here's the
interesting thing. Only one of the three
energy systems is capable of burning
fat. The first energy system we'll
mention is the creatine phosphate
system. Sometimes called the phosphor
creatine system. This system is for
super short explosive highintensity
efforts like during the first 5 to 10
seconds of a sprint or a heavy set of
low rep squats. It uses stored creatine
phosphate in your muscles to quickly
regenerate ATP. And if you look at the
diagram, creatine phosphate donates its
phosphate to ADP with the help of an
enzyme called creatine kinase to quickly
form more ATP. The benefit of this
system is that no oxygen is needed and
it's super fast. But the con is you can
only store so much creatine phosphate in
the muscles. So it runs out quickly,
like in 5 to 10 seconds. But with
creatine supplementation, you can store
more creatine phosphate in the muscles
and extend that time by a few seconds or
so, which explains how creatine can
improve performance. And there are more
details on that in our creatine video
that you're also more than welcome to
watch. But notice no fat is burned with
this energy system. The next energy
system is anorobic glycolysis. Anorobic
means without oxygen and glycolysis
refers to the breakdown of glucose. This
system kicks in for medium duration
highintensity activities such as 10 to
120 seconds of allout efforts or
highintensity intervals. The benefit of
this system is that it is also
relatively fast at generating ATP. But
without oxygen, the breakdown of one
glucose molecule only produces a net of
two ATP molecules. So eventually in
about 90 to 120 seconds, the two ATP
molecules produced per glucose molecule
just won't be enough for you to sustain
that highintensity effort for much
longer than 120 seconds. And you'll have
to stop or at least slow down. Plus, a
byproduct of this energy system is
lactic acid, which quickly dissociates
into lactate and a hydrogen ion. And
those hydrogen ions can temporarily
increase the acidity in the skeletal
muscle fiber also leading to fatigue.
And like the creatine phosphate system,
this system is not capable of burning
fat. And finally, we have the third
energy system, the aerobic energy
system. Sometimes also referred to as
oxidative phosphorilation. Aerobic and
oxidative both refer to the use of
oxygen. And phosphorilation means adding
a phosphate to ADP adenosine diphosphate
to create more ATP adenosine
triphosphate. In other words, we are
going to create a whole bunch of ATP
from this aerobic energy system. And you
could pretty much say that it's one of
the main reasons why we breathe because
it doesn't just utilize oxygen, it also
produces carbon dioxide as a byproduct.
And this is the only energy system that
can break down fats. So, this might
start getting you to think that certain
forms of exercise might be better at
stimulating this system and therefore
better at burning fat. The aerobic
energy system happens in the
mitochondria of the cell and can
actually use carbs, proteins, and fats
as fuel to make more ATP. But again,
it's the only pathway for burning fat.
And the reason why fats can only be
broken down by this energy system has to
do with oxygen. Now, you can get into a
ton of details as to why oxygen is
needed to burn fat. And any of you who
have ever had to memorize or learn beta
oxidation, the KB cycle, and the
electron transport chain know that it
can quickly turn into a detailed mess.
But for today's video, we will just say
that fat breakdown or lipolysis releases
fatty acids into your blood. And those
fatty acids will eventually enter cells
and muscle fibers that have
mitochondria. These fatty acids then get
shuttled into the mitochondria and go
through a process called beta oxidation
where they're oxidized. And the products
of beta oxidation, the acetal cos for
you physiology nerds out there, are then
funneled into the KB cycle where they
are further oxidized or burned with
oxygen which results in a ton of ATP.
And I'll mention those ATP numbers in
just a second. But without oxygen and
this pathway, fats could not be used for
energy. In some ways, you could argue
that carbs are a little more versatile
because carbs can be utilized in
anorobic glycolysis. And if there's
enough oxygen present in the cell, some
of the products of carbohydrate
breakdown through glycolysis can be
funneled into the mitochondria and make
30 to 32 ATP molecules per molecule of
glucose. But that's nothing compared to
the oxidation or breakdown of one fatty
acid chain. For example, with a 16c
carbon fatty acid like palmate, the
breakdown of this fatty acid produces
about 113 ATP molecules. So you might
initially think, "Wow, that's
incredible. So why not always use fat if
we can get over 113 ATP molecules per
fatty acid?" Well, just like the other
two energy systems, there are some pros
and cons. The pros of the aerobic system
is the number of ATP you can get and
what seems like an almost limitless
supply of energy because one pound of
fat packs about 3500 calories. So 180 lb
person at 15% body fat has around 94,500
calories in reserve. But this system is
slow. It takes many more steps, chemical
compounds, and enzymes to generate ATP
from fat as compared to the other two
faster energy systems. And if we're
talking about mobilizing the fat from
atapost tissue in order to lose weight,
then that takes even more time to pull
those fatty acids from the fat cells,
move them through the bloodstream and
into an exercising skeletal muscle
fiber. Also, this system requires a lot
of oxygen. At rest, this isn't a problem
because our metabolic demand and
therefore our demand for oxygen is low
and our heart and lungs have no problem
supplying our cells with that amount of
oxygen. This is even true with slight
increases in demand with walking and
maybe even light jogging. But as we
increase the intensity of our activity
during exercise, our demand for oxygen
goes up and then we are at the mercy of
the cardiovascular and respiratory
systems. Our lungs can only exchange so
much oxygen and carbon dioxide. Our
heart can only pump so much blood. Our
blood can only deliver so much oxygen.
So when we get to certain levels of
higher intensity, we literally cannot
get enough oxygen to the working muscles
fast enough and don't have the time to
utilize all the extra steps required to
just burn fat. So, we have to utilize
carbohydrates as well as the other
anorobic energy systems such as the
creatine phosphate system and anorobic
glycolysis. But here is something that's
incredible. The level of intensity at
where you start needing to cross over
and rely on carbohydrates and those
other anorobic energy systems depends on
your fitness level. As someone gets more
fit, especially through aerobic
training, the heart will get stronger
and will be able to pump more blood.
You'll increase the number of red blood
cells. You'll increase the number of
capillaries going to skeletal muscles
and you'll even increase your blood
volume. All of this results in more
oxygen being able to be delivered to an
exercising skeletal muscle. So then you
could stay within this aerobic energy
system or this aerobic zone at a higher
level of intensity before needing to
start shifting to the anorobic energy
systems. Say for example, when you were
less fit, you could stay in this aerobic
zone at 5 miles an hour on a treadmill.
But as you got more fit, you could stay
within this same zone at 6 mph. All
because your cardiovascular system got
better at delivering more oxygen to
supply this aerobic energy system and
therefore is able to utilize more fat.
And this finally gets us into the
discussion of what is the best type of
exercise to burn fat. Now, what's
interesting about finding the best form
of exercise to burn fat is that
technically you burn the highest
percentage of fat at rest. But
percentage doesn't necessarily equal a
high total amount of fat being burned.
And to really understand why this is, I
want to show you a chart that I love to
reference from a case study of a male
recreational athlete in his 40s who was
training for a marathon. Because this
chart can really help to clear up some
of the confusion around fat loss. So,
let's walk through what's actually
happening here. On the left side, we
have heart rate, which you can think of
as a rough proxy for exercise intensity.
As heart rate increases, you'll notice
that the percentage of energy coming
from fat goes down, while the percentage
of energy coming from carbohydrates goes
up. And this supports what we've
actually talked about and learned today.
Carbohydrates are simply just a faster
fuel source. So, as intensity rises,
your body has to rely on carbs more
heavily. But here's a key concept. Even
though the percentage of fat being used
is dropping, the total number of
calories burned per minute is
increasing. So if you look at the next
column over showing fat calories burned
per minute, fat oxidation actually
increases as intensity rises even though
the percentage is lower because that
lower percentage is coming from a much
larger total amount of calories being
burned. But this increase in fat
oxidation only occurs up to a point. In
the case of this individual, it peaks
around a heart rate of 130 beats per
minute. And you can see that's the
highest amount of fat oxidation at this
heart rate. And this is what people
refer to as the fat burning zone or zone
2. And to be clear, this concept is
rooted in real physiology. There really
is an intensity where fat oxidation is
maximized during exercise. But I do want
to mention that your individual fat
burning zone wouldn't necessarily be at
138 beats per minute. It depends on your
age, fitness level, your resting heart
rate, your max heart rate. But the
overall pattern of this chart of
percentages going down for fat and
percentages of carbohydrates going up
with exercise intensity, that overall
pattern would be the same for you. It's
just that maybe your fat burning zone
might be in the 140s or the 120s. It is
essentially what the fitness world
refers to as zone 2 training, which is
about 60 to 70% of your max heart rate.
And if you know your resting and your
max heart rate, there's a really cool
website that can calculate all your
heart rate zones that I'll link in the
description. But this fat burning zone
only tells us where fat burning peaks
during the workout, not where fat loss
is maximized over time. As intensity
continues to rise past this point, yes,
that oxidation per minute starts to
decline slightly as you can see here,
but the total calories being burned
continues to climb. And this is where
people can sometimes get tripped up.
They see that the fat calories burned
per minute are a little lower at the
higher intensities and then assume that
the fat loss is going to be worse unless
they scale back to that lower intensity
of the fat burning zone. But that
conclusion doesn't hold true once we
zoom out beyond the exercise bout itself
because fat loss doesn't just happen
minute by minute. It happens over hours,
days, and weeks. So let's say instead of
doing a 45minute steadystate zone 2 run
or a zone 2 cycling session in this fat
burning zone that you did a 45minute
higher intensity steadystate run or
cycling session in zone 3 or zone 4.
Even though the higher intensity
exercise would burn less fat per minute
during the exercise session, it would
again burn a higher total of overall
calories. And this creates a larger
overall energy deficit and places
greater recovery demands on the body.
And when you recover, you're restoring
ATP, reynthesizing phosphor creatine,
reestablishing ion gradients, and
replenishing glycogen. So you have this
energy debt that needs to be repaid
after exercise and even between
intervals that we'll get into in just a
second. And some of this energy debt
will get repaid from carbohydrates. But
during recovery, a huge portion of that
repayment comes from fat. So much so
that in many cases, this can result in
greater total fat oxidation over a
24-hour period compared to a lower
intensity exercise session alone. So
this also can apply to highintensity
interval training. During a hard
interval, which could be something that
you could only do for 3 to four minutes,
fat oxidation is relatively low. Or if
they were really high intensity
intervals that you could only do for
like 30 to 90 seconds, which would go
even beyond the intensity of this chart,
fat oxidation would be even lower,
almost even approaching zero in some
cases. And so therefore, almost all of
the energy would come from carbs through
anorobic glycolysis with small
contributions coming from phosphor
creatine. And again, one might initially
think this is a very inefficient way to
burn fat, but between intervals when
you're recovering with walking or maybe
jogging at a zone 2 intensity, what are
you doing? You are breathing like crazy
and very much using the aerobic energy
system and fats to regenerate ATP,
reynthesize phosphor creatine,
reestablish ion gradients, etc. And so
again, fat becomes an important fuel
even with highintensity intervals. And
this will also continue on after the
whole workout is completed. So instead
of asking, am I burning fat right this
second during this exact bout of
exercise? A better question might be, am
I creating the conditions that allow my
body to burn fat overall? And so the
answer to this is burning a meaningful
amount of total energy through the
combination of different training
intensities throughout the week. And the
reason why the answer is not just do the
highest exercise intensity you can do
for every exercise session is because
this often leads to burnout or
overtraining. You can't just maintain
extremely high levels of intensity
session after session after session.
Plus, there are still benefits to
spending time in zone 2 or that fat
burning zone. Even though technically
you could burn a higher amount of fat at
higher intensities, zone 2 still burns a
decent amount of fat. And there are
plenty of other benefits to spending
some time each week in zone 2. And this
includes the benefits it has in
stimulating mitochondrial biosynthesis,
which means the mitochondria you have
get bigger and you create more of them,
which has incredible metabolic benefits,
such as reducing your risk of type 2
diabetes, for example. Plus, it shifts
the graph, meaning zone 2 trains your
body to metabolize even more fats in
that fat burning zone. So, you'll start
to see this number creep up at the same
level of intensity. And this will also
trickle into your overall fat burning
capacity even when you're doing your
higher intensity days. And we can't
forget about the benefits of preserving
muscle mass, which resistance training
also is going to burn some calories,
plus the benefits of increased strength,
improved bone density, and even helping
to keep your baseline energy needs a
little higher. So, if you've watched our
channel before, you know that I tend to
like a split that includes doing
resistance training on say like
Tuesdays, Thursdays, and Saturdays where
you alternate upper body days with lower
body days. And then you could do
cardiovascular training on Mondays,
Wednesdays, and Fridays. And you could
do all sorts of combinations of cardio
training. I have some patients that like
to alternate every cardio day where one
cardio day they do zone two and the next
cardio day they do high intensity and
they keep flip-flopping. So, one week
they get two zone twos in and one high
intensity and the next week it
flip-flops. Or some like to do zone two
on like Mondays and Wednesdays and then
go crazy with a highintensity day on
Friday. And one of the beauties of
exercise programming is that you can
tweak so many different variables that
can be tailored to a person's specific
goals and can still be very beneficial
for one's overall health. And we still
have our sample workout chart that I can
put a link for in the description if you
want to check that out. But thank you so
much for sticking around to the end of
this video, everyone. I know we got into
the physiological weeds a little bit. So
hopefully you learned some very useful
information. And let us know what you
thought in the comments or any questions
that you may have because I still do
actually read through the comments for
feedback and new video ideas. And of
course, we'll see you in the next video.